Most of the time, art and science stare at each other
في أغلب الأوقات , يحدّق الفن والعلم لبعضهما البعض
across a gulf of mutual incomprehension.
عبر خليج من المشتركات الغير مفهومة .
There is great confusion when the two look at each other.
يوجد إرتباك كبير عندما ينظر الإثنان إلى بعضهم البعض .
Art, of course, looks at the world through the psyche,
الفن , بالطبع , ينظرإلى العالم عبر النفس ,
the emotions -- the unconscious at times -- and of course the aesthetic.
الأحاسيس -- حتى الآوعي في بعض الاوقات -- وبالطبع الإبداع .
Science tends to look at the world through the rational, the quantitative --
يميل العلم الى النظر إلى العالم عبرالمنطق والكم --
things that can be measured and described --
أشياء يمكن أن تُقاس وتوصف --
but it gives art a terrific context of understanding.
لكن العلم يقدم الفن في محتوى رائع من ( المعرفة والفهم ).
In the Extreme Ice Survey,
في فحص فقدان الجليد ,
we're dedicated to bringing those two parts of human understanding together,
قررنا إحضار هذين الجزئين من فهم الإنسان معاً ،
to merging the art and science
بدمج الفن والعلم
to the end of helping us understand nature
إلى الحد الذي يساعدنا لفهم الطبيعة
and humanity's relationship with nature better.
والعلاقة بين الطبيعة والجنس البشري بصورة أفضل .
Specifically, I as a person
خصوصا , إنني شخص
who's been a professional nature photographer my whole adult life,
كنت مصور طبيعة محترف طوال شبابي ،
am firmly of the belief that photography, video, film
أنا مؤمن بصورة قاطعة بأن التصوير, الفيديو و الفيلم
have tremendous powers for helping us understand
لهم قوة هائلة لمساعدتنا في فهم ,
and shape the way we think about nature
وتشكيل الطريق لنتأمل في الطبيعة
and about ourselves in relationship to nature.
وعن أنفسنا في علاقتنا مع الطبيعة .
In this project, we're specifically interested, of course, in ice.
في هذا المشروع , نحن مهتمون خصوصا , بالطبع , بالجليد
I'm fascinated by the beauty of it, the mutability of it,
أنا مفتون بجماله , بتحولاته ,
the malleability of it,
بقابليته للتطويع ،
and the fabulous shapes in which it can carve itself.
وشكله الغير قابل للتصديق الذي يستطيع نحت نفسه .
These first images are from Greenland.
هذه الصور الأولية من غرين لاند .
But ice has another meaning.
لكن الجليد له معنى آخر .
Ice is the canary in the global coal mine.
الجليد هو طائر الكناري في منجم الفحم العالمي .
It's the place where we can see and touch and hear and feel climate change in action.
هو المكان الذي نقدر أن نرى ونلمس ونسمع ونشعر بتغير المناخ يحدث .
Climate change is a really abstract thing in most of the world.
تغير المناخ هو في الحقيقة شيء تجريدي في معظم أنحاء العالم .
Whether or not you believe in it is based on your sense of
سواء صدقت أم لم تصدق فإنه يعتمد على إحساسك ب
is it raining more or is it raining less?
هل تهطل الأمطار أكثر أو أقل ,
Is it getting hotter or is it getting colder?
سواء أصبح الطقس ساخنا أو باردا .
What do the computer models say about this, that and the other thing?
أوعن ماذا تقول عنه نماذج الحاسوب , تلك والقياسات الأخرى .
All of that, strip it away. In the world of the arctic and alpine environments,
كل ذلك , يفصله بعيدا . في عالم البيئات القطبية و إرتفاعات الجبال ,
where the ice is, it's real and it's present.
التي يتواجد فيها الجليد [ تغيرالمناخ ] يكون حقيقياً ومتواجد .
The changes are happening. They're very visible.
التغيرات تحدث . إنها مرئية .
They're photographable. They're measurable.
من الممكن تصويرها . يمكن قياسها .
95 percent of the glaciers in the world are retreating or shrinking.
95 في المائة من أنهار الجليد في العالم تتراجع وتتقلص .
That's outside Antarctica.
التي هي خارج القارة القطبية الجنوبية .
95 percent of the glaciers in the world are retreating or shrinking,
95 في المائة من أنهار الجليد في العالم تتراجع وتتقلص
and that's because the precipitation patterns and the temperature patterns are changing.
بسبب نماذج التغيرات المناخية وأنماط درجات الحرارة تتغير .
There is no significant scientific dispute about that.
لا يوجد خلاف علمي واضح حول ذلك .
It's been observed, it's measured, it's bomb-proof information.
لقد كانت مراقبة , مقاسة , مبرهنة بكتل المعلومات .
And the great irony and tragedy of our time
والسخرية الكبيرة والمأساوية لعصرنا
is that a lot of the general public thinks that science is still arguing about that.
هي تلك الأفكار الكثيرة العامة من البعض أن العلم مازال يتجادل عليها .
Science is not arguing about that.
العلم لا يتجادل عن ذلك .
In these images we see ice from enormous glaciers,
في هذه الصور نرى الجليد من مجاري جليدية ضخمة ,
ice sheets that are hundreds of thousands of years old
ملاءات الجليد التي تكونت في مئات آلاف السنوات
breaking up into chunks, and chunk by chunk by chunk,
تتحطم الى قطع صغيرة , وقطعة , بقطعة , بقطعة ,
iceberg by iceberg, turning into global sea level rise.
جبل جليدي , بجبل جليدي , يتحول و يرتفع إلى مستوى بحر العالمي .
So, having seen all of this in the course of a 30-year career,
لذلك ، بعد أن شهدت هذا كله في غضون 30 سنة من حياتي المهنية ،
I was still a skeptic about climate change until about 10 years ago,
كنت لا أزال متشكك حول تغير المناخ حتى منذ حوالي 10 سنوات الماضية ,
because I thought the story of climate change was based on computer models.
بسبب إعتقادي أن قصة تغير المناخ كانت تعتمد على نماذج الحاسوب .
I hadn't realized it was based on concrete measurements
لم أدرك إنها كانت تعتمد على قياسات ملموسة
of what the paleoclimates -- the ancient climates -- were,
للمناخات القديمة -- المناخات العتيقة -- التي كانت ,
as recorded in the ice sheets, as recorded in deep ocean sediments,
كما سجلت في لوحات الجليد , في أعماق رواسب المحيطات ,
as recorded in lake sediments, tree rings,
في رواسب أعماق البحيرات , في حلقات الشجر ,
and a lot of other ways of measuring temperature.
والكثير من الطرق لقياس درجة الحرارة .
When I realized that climate change was real, and it was not based on computer models,
عندها أدركت ان تغير المناخ كان حقيقيا , وإنه لم يكن يعتمد على نماذج الحاسوب ,
I decided that one day I would do a project
قررت يوما ما إنني أريد ان أفعل مشروعا
looking at trying to manifest climate change photographically.
أنظر وأحاول أن أشاهد التغير المناخي فوتوغرافيا .
And that led me to this project.
وهذا قادني إلى هذا المشروع .
Initially, I was working on a National Geographic assignment --
مبدئيا , كنت أعمل في مهمة جغرافية عالمية ،
conventional, single frame, still photography.
صور تقليدية ، إطار فردي ، تصوير عادي .
And one crazy day, I got the idea that I should --
وفي يوم صعب , توصلت إلى الفكرة التي ينبغي --
after that assignment was finished --
بعد أن أنهيت تلك المهمة --
I got the idea that I should shoot in time-lapse photography,
خطرت لي فكرة أن أصوّر بتصوير الإطار الزمني ،
that I should station a camera or two at a glacier
أن أضع كاميرا , أو إثنان , في المجاري الجليدية
and let it shoot every 15 minutes, or every hour or whatever
والسماح لها أن تلتقط صورة كل 15 دقيقة ، أو في كل ساعة ، أو أيا كان
and watch the progression of the landscape over time.
وأراقب تطور المناظر الطبيعية عبر الوقت .
Well, within about three weeks,
حسناً , خلال ثلاث اسابيع ,
I incautiously turned that idea of a couple of time-lapse cameras
بإغفال مني حولت تلك الفكرة من إثنان من الكاميرات الضوئية
into 25 time-lapse cameras.
إلى 25 كاميرا تصوير للإطار الزمني .
And the next six months of my life were the hardest time in my career,
في الست أشهر القادمة من حياتي كانت الوقت الأصعب في مجالي ,
trying to design, build and deploy out in the field these 25 time-lapse cameras.
محاولا ان أصمم , أبني وأنشر في الميدان تلك ال25 كاميرا ذات الإطار الزمني .
They are powered by the sun. Solar panels power them.
مصدر طاقتهم هي الشمس . الألواح الشمسية تغذيهم .
Power goes into a battery. There is a custom made computer
تسري الطاقة إلى البطارية. يوجد كمبيوتر مصمم خصيصاً
that tells the camera when to fire.
الذي يعرف الكاميرا متى تلتقط .
And these cameras are positioned on rocks on the sides of the glaciers,
وهؤلاء الكاميرات موضوعة فوق الصخور وجوانب المجاري الجليدية ,
and they look in on the glacier from permanent, bedrock positions,
وهم ينظرون إلي المجاري المائية من المواضع الدائمة والصخور الكائنة ,
and they watch the evolution of the landscape.
ويشاهدون تغير و تطور المشاهد الطبيعية .
We just had a number of cameras out on the Greenland Ice Sheet.
لدينا فقط عدد من الكاميرات خارجا على لوح جليد المنطقة الخضراء .
We actually drilled holes into the ice, way deep down below the thawing level,
نحن في الحقيقة حفرنا حفر في الجليد , طريق عميق أسفل مستوى ذوبان الثلج
and had some cameras out there for the past month and a half or so.
وتركنا الكاميرات خارجا هناك حوالي شهر ونصف الماضية أونحو ذلك .
Actually, there's still a camera out there right now.
غالبا , ما زالت توجد كاميرا خارجة هناك حتى الآن .
In any case, the cameras shoot roughly every hour.
على أية حال , تصور الكاميرات تقريبا كل ساعة ,
Some of them shoot every half hour, every 15 minutes, every five minutes.
كل نصف ساعة , كل15 دقيقة , وكل 5 دقائق .
Here's a time lapse of one of the time-lapse units being made.
هنا نجد هذه الفترة الزمنية من إحدى وحدات الفترات الزمنبة التي صنعت .
(Laughter)
(ضحك).
I personally obsessed about every nut, bolt and washer in these crazy things.
أنا شخصيا قلق على كل بنس , مسمار والمغسلة في تلك الأشياء الصغيرة .
I spent half my life at our local hardware store
قضيت نصف حياتي في محلات بيع الأدوات الصلبة .
during the months when we built these units originally.
خلال الشهور التي بنينا فيها تلك الوحدات على نحو أصيل .
We're working in most of the major glaciated regions of the northern hemisphere.
نحن نعمل في أهم أنهار المناطق الجليدية في شمال نصف الكرة الأرضية .
Our time-lapse units are in Alaska, the Rockies, Greenland and Iceland,
تكون وحدات الفترة الزمنية في ألاسكا , ركيز , جرين لاند وأيس لاند ,
and we have repeat photography positions,
وقد أعدنا أماكن التصوير ,
that is places we just visit on an annual basis,
تلك هي الأماكن التي زرناها في الدفعة السنوية الأساسية ,
in British Columbia, the Alps and Bolivia.
في كولومبيا البريطانية , الألب وبوليفيا .
It's a big undertaking. I stand here before you tonight
هذا أكبر مشروع . أقف هنا أمامكم الليلة
as an ambassador for my whole team.
الليلة كسفير عن كل فريقي .
There's a lot of people working on this right now.
يوجد الكثير من الناس يعملون على هذا حتى الآن .
We've got 33 cameras out this moment.
قد حصلنا على33 كاميرا حتي هذه اللحظة .
We just had 33 cameras shoot about half an hour ago
لدينا فقط 33 من الكاميرات المصورة على نصف ساعة مضت
all across the northern hemisphere, watching what's happened.
عبر كل نصف الكرة الشمالي , نشاهد ماذا حدث .
And we've spent a lot of time in the field. It's been a fantastic amount of work.
وقد قضينا الكثير من الوقت في الميدان . قد كان معدلا رائعا من العمل .
We've been out for two and a half years,
قد كنا خارجا لسنتان ونصف ,
and we've got about another two and a half years yet to go.
ولدينا حوالي سنتان و نصف أخرى حتى الآن لنمضي .
That's only half our job.
ذلك فقط نصف عملنا .
The other half of our job is to tell the story to the global public.
النصف الآخر من عملنا يكون أن نسرد القصة للشعوب العالمية .
You know, scientists have collected this kind of information
تعرفون , قد جمع العلماء هذا النوع من المعلومات
off and on over the years, but a lot of it stays within the science community.
عمل و راحة علي مدي السنوات , لكن يبقى الكثير منه ضمن مجتمع العلم .
Similarly, a lot of art projects stay in the art community,
على نحو متشابه , تبقى الكثير من المشاريع الفنية علي الجماعية الفنية ,
and I feel very much a responsibility through mechanisms like TED,
وأحس بالكثير من المسؤولية عبر تقنيات مثل تيد ,
and like our relationship with the Obama White House,
ومثل علاقتنا مع أوباما بالبيت الأبيض ,
with the Senate, with John Kerry, to influence policy
مع مجلس الشيوخ , مع مكتب جون كيري , لثأتيره في السياسية
as much as possible with these pictures as well.
بأكبر قدر ممكن مع هذه الصور أيضا .
We've done films. We've done books. We have more coming.
قد أنجزنا أفلام . قد أنجزنا كتب . ولدينا أشياء كثيرة قادمة .
We have a site on Google Earth
ولدينا موقع على غوغل أرض
that Google Earth was generous enough to give us,
غوغل أرض التي كانت كريمة كفاية لتقدم لنا —
and so forth, because we feel very much the need to tell this story,
كل هذا بسبب أننا ندرك الإحتياج أن نروي هذه الحكاية ,
because it is such an immediate evidence of ongoing climate change right now.
نظرا لأنها دليل مباشر للتغير المتطور للمناخ القائم الآن .
Now, one bit of science before we get into the visuals.
الآن , مقدار ضئيل من العلم قبل أن نتوصل بالمرئية .
If everybody in the developed world understood this graph,
إن فهم كل فرد في الدول المتقدمة هذه الرسوم البيانية ,
and emblazoned it on the inside of their foreheads,
ودمجها في مقدمة عقله ,
there would be no further societal argument about climate change
سوف لا تكون هناك مناقشات مجتمعية إضافية حول تغير المناخ
because this is the story that counts.
لأن هذه هي القصة التي تستحق .
Everything else you hear is just propaganda and confusion.
أي شيء إضافي تسمعه هو فقط دعاية وفوضى .
Key issues: this is a 400,000 year record.
القضايا الرئيسية : هذه تسجيلات 400,000 سنة .
This exact same pattern is seen going back now
نفس النموذج الذي رأيتموه من قبل سيعود مجددا
almost a million years before our current time.
بملايين السنوات قبل وقتنا الحاضر الآن .
And several things are important.
بعض الأشياء مهمة جداً .
Number one: temperature and carbon dioxide in the atmosphere
رقم واحد : درجة الحرارة وثاني أكسيد الكربون في الغلاف الجوي
go up and down basically in sync.
تتحرك صعودا وهبوطا في تزامن .
You can see that from the orange line and the blue line.
يمكن ان ترى ذلك من الخط البرتقالي والخط الأزرق .
Nature naturally has allowed carbon dioxide to go up to 280 parts per million.
قد سمحت الطبيعة فطريا لثاني أكسيد الكربون ليصعد عاليا ل280 جزء في المليون .
That's the natural cycle.
هذه هذه هي الدورة الطبيعية .
Goes up to 280 and then drops
تصعد ل280 و عنذئذ تهبط
for various reasons that aren't important to discuss right here.
لأسباب متعددة التي ليس مهما أن نتاقشها الآن .
But 280 is the peak.
لكن 280 هي القمة .
Right now, if you look at the top right part of that graph,
الآن تماما , إذا نظرتم في الجهة اليمنى من ذلك الرسم البياني ,
we're at 385 parts per million.
نحن في 385 جزء من المليون .
We are way, way outside the normal, natural variability.
نحن في طريق , بعيدة جداً عن العادي , المتغير الطبيعي .
Earth is having a fever.
الأرض مريضة بحمى .
In the past hundred years, the temperature of the Earth
في المائة السنة الماضية , قد صعدت درجة حرارة الأرض
has gone up 1.3 degrees Fahrenheit, .75 degrees Celsius,
ب1.3 درجة فهرنهايتي , 0.75 درجة مئوية
and it's going to keep going up
وفي طريق مواصلة الصعود
because we keep dumping fossil fuels into the atmosphere.
بسبب استمرارنا التخلص من النفط المتفحمة في الجو .
At the rate of about two and a half parts per million per year.
في نسبة إثنان ونصف أجزاء من المليون في السنة .
It's been a remorseless, steady increase.
قد كانت قاسية , مستمرة الارتفاع .
We have to turn that around.
يجب علينا أن نحول ذلك إلي الإتجاه الآخر .
That's the crux, and someday I hope to emblazon that
تلك هي المشكلة المحورية , ويوما ما أتمنى أن ندمج ذلك
across Times Square in New York and a lot of other places.
عبر ميدان تايم في نيويورك وفي الكثير من الأماكن الآخرى .
But anyway, off to the world of ice.
لكن على أية حال , بعيدا عن عالم الجليد .
We're now at the Columbia Glacier in Alaska.
نحن الآن في الأنهار الجليدية الكولومبية في ألاسكا .
This is a view of what's called the calving face.
هذه نظرة لما يطلق عليه وجه الإنهيار الجليدي .
This is what one of our cameras saw over the course of a few months.
هذا ما صورتة واحدة من كاميراتنا خلال فترة شهور قليلة .
You see the glacier flowing in from the right,
رأيتم تدفق الانهار الجليدية من اليمين ,
dropping off into the sea, camera shooting every hour.
تسقط جانبا في البحر , تصور الكاميرا كل ساعة .
If you look in the middle background,
إذا نظرتم في وسط الخلفية ,
you can see the calving face bobbing up and down like a yo-yo.
يمكنكم ان تروا المظهر الخارجي الممزق يتمايل إلى الأعلى والأسفل مثل الشيء المتقلب "اليويو" .
That means that glacier's floating and it's unstable,
يعني هذا أن المجاري المتجمدة متقلقة وغير مستقرة ,
and you're about to see the consequences of that floating.
وأنتم على وشك أن تروا النتائج المترتبة على هذا التقلقل .
To give you a little bit of a sense of scale,
لتعطيك قليلا من الشعور بصورة تدريجية ،
that calving face in this picture
ذلك المظهر الخارجي الممزق في هذه الصورة
is about 325 feet tall. That's 32 stories.
حوالي تكون 325 قدم طولا . ذلك 32 من الحكايات .
This is not a little cliff. This is like a major office building in an urban center.
هذا ليس منحدراً صغيرا . هذا مثل أهم مبنى عمل في المنطقة الحضرية .
The calving face is the wall where the visible ice breaks off,
الإنهيار الخارجي الممزق يمثل الحائط الذي يتكسر الجليد المرئي فيه جانبا ,
but in fact, it goes down below sea level another couple thousand feet.
لكن حقيقة , تذهب في الأعماق أسفل مستوى البحر الفين من الأقدام .
So there's a wall of ice a couple thousand feet deep
إذن يوجد حائط من الجليد علي عمق ألفين قدم
going down to bedrock if the glacier's grounded on bedrock,
تذهب أسفل الى الاعماق , ان كانت القطع الجليدية رست على أعماق الا رض ,
and floating if it isn't.
وتتقلقل إذا لم تكن كذلك .
Here's what Columbia's done. This is in south central Alaska.
هذا ما فعلته كولومبيا . هذا في وسط الاسكا الجنوبي .
This was an aerial picture I did one day in June three years ago.
هذه كانت صورة جوية قمت بها يوما ما في يونيو ثلات سنوات مضت .
This is an aerial picture we did this year.
هذه صورة جوية قمت بها هذه السنة .
That's the retreat of this glacier.
يكون ذلك الانسحاب لهذا المجرى الجليدي .
The main stem, the main flow of the glacier is coming from the right
الجزء الرئيسي , التدفق الرئيسي للجليد من جهه اليمين
and it's going very rapidly up that stem.
ويذهب بسرعة كبيرة أعلى ذلك الحاجز .
We're going to be up there in just a few more weeks,
نحن ذاهبون لكي نكون هناك فقط في خلال بعض اسابيع ,
and we expect that it's probably retreated another half a mile,
ونتوقع ان يكون هناك إحتمال إنسحاب نصفا اخر من الميل ,
but if I got there and discovered that it had collapsed
لكني إن وصلت إلي هناك وإكتشفت أنه كان هناك إنهيار
and it was five miles further back, I wouldn't be the least bit surprised.
وانه كان خمسة اميال يعيدا في الوراء , لن أكون متعجبا ابداً .
Now it's really hard to grasp the scale of these places,
حقيقة الأن من الصعوبة فهم تسلسل هذه الأماكن
because as the glaciers --
بسبب أن المجاري الجليدية --
one of the things is that places like Alaska and Greenland are huge,
واحدة من الأشياء الأماكن مثل ألاسكا والجرين لاند ضخمة ,
they're not normal landscapes --
ليست مناطق طبيعية عادية --
but as the glaciers are retreating, they're also deflating,
لكن مع تراجع المجاري الجليدية , وانخفاضها أيضا ,
like air is being let out of a balloon.
مثل الهواء الذي يكون خارجا من المنطاد .
And so, there are features on this landscape.
وإذن , توجد ميزات على هذه المناظر الطبيعية .
There's a ridge right in the middle of the picture, up above where that arrow comes in,
توجد سلسلة جبال يمينا في وسط الصورة , فوق أعلى مكان بلوغ السهم ,
that shows you that a little bit.
ذلك يظهر لكم قليلا من التوضيح .
There's a marker line called the trim line
توجد خط علامة تدعى خط الزينة
above our little red illustration there.
فوق صورتنا التوضيحية الحمراء .
This is something no self-respecting photographer would ever do --
هذه صورة لا يوجد مصور محترم يأخذها --
you put some cheesy illustration on your shot, right? --
ضعوا بعض الصور الإيضاحية اللزجة في رميته , جيد ؟
and yet you have to do it sometimes to narrate these points.
وبعد يجب ان تفعله في بعض الأوقات لنروي هذه النقط .
But, in any case, the deflation of this glacier since 1984
لكن , في أية حال , كان انكماش هذا المجرى الجليدي منذ1984
has been higher than the Eiffel Tower, higher than the Empire State Building.
أعلي من برج أيفل , أعلي من مبني إمباير ستات .
A tremendous amount of ice has been let out of these valleys
كمية ضخمة من هذا الجليد قد تركت هذه الوديان
as it's retreated and deflated, gone back up valley.
كما أنها تراجعت و انخفضت , ورجعت إلي أعلي الوادي .
These changes in the alpine world are accelerating.
هذه التغيرات في العالم الألبيني سريعة التغير .
It's not static.
ليست تابتة .
Particularly in the world of sea ice,
خصوصا في بحر الجليد ,
the rate of natural change is outstripping predictions of just a few years ago,
معدل التغير الطبيعي خارج التنبؤات آخر بضع سنوات مضت
and the processes either are accelerating
والعمليات إما أنها كانت معجلة
or the predictions were too low to begin with.
أو أن التنبؤات كانت بطيئة جدا لكي تبدأ .
But in any case, there are big, big changes happening as we speak.
لكن على أية حال , توجد تغيرات , تغيرات كبيرة تحدت لأننا نتكلم .
So, here's another time-lapse shot of Columbia.
هنا صورة آخري بطيئة من كولومبيا .
And you see where it ended in these various spring days,
وترون أين تنتهي في تلك الموسم الربيعي المتغير ,
June, May, then October.
يونيو, مايو , ثم أكتوبر .
Now we turn on our time lapse.
الآن نعود بالصورة إلي الوراء .
This camera was shooting every hour.
كانت تصور هذه الكاميرا كل ساعة .
Geologic process in action here.
العملية الجيولوجية في حركة هنا .
And everybody says, well don't they advance in the winter time?
وكلكم يقولون , حسناً ألا يعود إلي وضعه في وقت الشتاء .
No. It was retreating through the winter because it's an unhealthy glacier.
لا. كانت متراجعة خلال موسم الشتاء بسبب أنها نهر جليدي غير صحي .
Finally catches up to itself, it advances.
اخيرا أمسكت بنفسها , وأندفعت الى الأمام .
And you can look at these pictures over and over again
ويمكنكم ان تروا هذه الصور مرات عديدة
because there's such a strange, bizarre fascination in seeing
بسبب وجود مثل هذا السحر الغريب والعجيب في رؤيته
these things you don't normally get to see come alive.
هذه الأشياء التي عادة لا تستطيعوا أن تروها تأتي حية.
We've been talking about "seeing is believing "
نحن نتكلم عن أن الرؤية هي التصديق
and seeing the unseen at TED Global.
ونري الغير مرئي في تيد العالمية .
That's what you see with these cameras.
ذلك ما ترونه بهذه الكاميرات .
The images make the invisible visible.
الصور تجعل الغير مرئي مرئي .
These huge crevasses open up.
تفتح هذه الصدوع الضخمة .
These great ice islands break off --
هذه الجزر الجليدية العظيمة تتكسر --
and now watch this.
والآن شاهدوا هذا .
This has been the springtime this year --
كان هذا في الربيع هذا العام --
a huge collapse. That happened in about a month,
إنهيار ضخم . حدث ذلك في حوالي شهر ,
the loss of all that ice.
فقدان كل ذلك الجليد .
So that's where we started three years ago,
ذلك الذي بدأناه منذ ثلاث سنوات ماضية ,
way out on the left, and that's where we were a few months ago, the
الطريق الخارجة على اليسار , وهنالك حيث كنا في الشهور القليلة الماضية ,
last time we went into Columbia.
المرة الأخيرة التي ذهبنا فيها الى كولومبيا .
To give you a feeling for the scale of the retreat,
لإعطائكم إحساساً مقياس مدرج للتراجع ,
we did another cheesy illustration,
فعلنا صور توضيحية لزجة أخرى .
with British double-decker buses.
مع حافلات بريطانية ذات طبقين .
If you line up 295 of those nose to tail, that's about how far back that was.
إذا سطرتم 295 من أولئك الحافلات الانوف الى الذيل , ذلك حوالي كيف تبعد خلفا من ذلك الذي كانت .
It's a long way.
إنها طريق طويلة .
On up to Iceland.
الطريق إلي أيسلند .
One of my favorite glaciers, the Sólheimajökull.
واحد من مجاريا الجليدية المفضلة لدي , السولهيماجوكل .
And here, if you watch, you can see the terminus retreating.
وهنا , إذا شاهدتم , تقدروا أن تروا نهاية الانسحاب ,
You can see this river being formed.
تقدروا أن تروا وجود شكل هذا النهر ,
You can see it deflating.
تقدروا أن تروا انخفاضه .
Without the photographic process, you would never see this. This is invisible.
بدون عملية فتوغرافية , حتما لن تروا هذا أبدا . هذا غير مرئي .
You can stand up there your whole life and you would never see this,
يمكنكم أن تقفوا هناك كل حياتكم ولن تروا هذا ,
but the camera records it.
لكن الكاميرا تسجله .
So we wind time backwards now.
نحن ندور الوقت إلى الوراء الآن .
We go back a couple years in time.
نرجع بالوقت سنتين في كل مرة .
That's where it started.
ذلك حيث بدأت .
That's where it ended a few months ago.
هنا حيث إنتهت منذ بعض شهور ماضية .
And on up to Greenland.
وفي طريقنا إلي جرين لاند .
The smaller the ice mass, the faster it responds to climate.
كلما كانت الكتلة الجليدية صغيرة , كلما استجابت سريعا للتغير .
Greenland took a little while to start reacting
أخذت جرين لاند فترة قليلة لتبدأ في التفاعل
to the warming climate of the past century,
مع المناخ الدافئ للقرن الماضي ,
but it really started galloping along about 20 years ago.
لكنها حقيقة بدأت تعدوا بسرعة على طول ال 20 سنة مضت .
And there's been a tremendous increase in the temperature up there.
و قد كان هناك ارتفاع ضخم في درجة الحرارة أعلى هناك .
It's a big place. That's all ice.
منطقة كبيرة . كلها جليد .
All those colors are ice and it goes up to about two miles thick,
كل تلك الألوان هي جليد وتمثل حوالي ميلين من السماكة ,
just a gigantic dome that comes in from the coast and rises in the middle.
فقط قبة ضخمة تصل الى الساحل وترتفع في الوسط .
The one glacier up in Greenland
يوجد نهر جليدي واحد في الجرين لاند
that puts more ice into the global ocean
الذي يضع جليدا إضافيا في المحيط العالمي أكثر
than all the other glaciers in the northern hemisphere combined
من كل الأنهار الجليدية الأخرى من مجموع نصف الكرة الشمالي :
is the Ilulissat Glacier.
النهر الجليدي اليسيات .
We have some cameras on the south edge of the Ilulissat,
لدينا بعض الكاميرات على الحافة الجنوبية من نهر لالسيات ,
watching the calving face as it goes through this dramatic retreat.
نشاهد الوجه المنهار كما يذهب خلال هدا الانسحاب المثير .
Here's a two-year record of what that looks like.
هذه تسجيلات عامين تصور كيف يشبه هذا .
Helicopter in front of the calving face for scale, quickly dwarfed.
الهليكوبتر أمام الواجه المنهاره للقشرة , و الذي يصغر سريعا .
The calving face is four and a half miles across,
الواجه المنهاره عبارة عن أربعة ونصف أميال طول
and in this shot, as we pull back, you're only seeing about a mile and a half.
وفي هذه الصورة , كما نسترجع , ترون فقط حوالي ميل ونصف منه .
So, imagine how big this is
تستطيعوا أن تتخيلوا كم هذا كبيرا
and how much ice is charging out.
وكم نفقد من الجليد الكثير .
The interior of Greenland is to the right.
الجزء الداخلي من جرين لاند على اليمين .
It's flowing out to the Atlantic Ocean on the left.
تتدفق خارجا الى المحيط الاطلسي على اليسار .
Icebergs, many, many, many, many times the size of this building, are roaring out to sea.
جبال الجليد , أكبر بكثير كثير كثير من هدا البناء طائفا خارجا في البحر .
We just downloaded these pictures a couple weeks ago,
هؤلاء الصور حملناها منذ اسبوعان مضت
as you can see. June 25th,
كما ترون , 25يونيو ,
monster calving events happened.
مع الإنهيارات الضخمة الأحداث تبدأ .
I'll show you one of those in a second.
سأظهر لكم واحد من أولئك في لحظة .
This glacier has doubled its flow speed in the past 15 years.
قد ضاعفت هده الأنهار الجليدية سرعتها المتدفقة في ال 15 سنة الماضية .
It now goes at 125 feet a day, dumping all this ice into the ocean.
وتذهب الان بسرعة 125 قدم في اليوم , تقرغ كل هذا الجليد في المحيط .
It tends to go in these pulses, about every three days,
تميل إلى الذهاب معاً كدفعات , حوالي كل ثلات أيام ,
but on average, 125 feet a day,
على متوسط ,125 قدم في اليوم ,
twice the rate it did 20 years ago.
ضعف المعدل التي كانت تسير به منذ 20سنة مضت .
Okay. We had a team out watching this glacier,
حسنا , لدينا فريق خارجي يشاهد هدا المجرى الجليدي ,
and we recorded the biggest calving event that's ever been put on film.
وقد سجلنا الحدث الإنهياري الأكبر الذي لم يصور كفيلم من قبل .
We had nine cameras going.
كان لدينا تسع كاميرات تعمل .
This is what a couple of the cameras saw.
هذا ما صورته إثنين من الكاميرات .
A 400-foot-tall calving face breaking off.
انفصال 400 قدم طولا من الجليد وإنهيارها .
Huge icebergs rolling over.
جبال جليد ضخمة , ضخمة تجري .
Okay, how big was that? It's hard to get it.
حسنا , كم كان كبيرا ذلك ؟ كان صعبا أن تعرفه .
So an illustration again, gives you a feeling for scale.
هكذا الصورة التوضيحية أيضا , تعطيك الشعور بالقياس .
A mile of retreat in 75 minutes
( تقريبا ) مَيل من الانسحاب في 75 دقيقة
across the calving face, in that particular event, three miles wide.
عبر المظهر الخارجي المنفصل لتلك الثقب الخاص , ثلاث أميال عرضا .
The block was three-fifths of a mile deep,
كانت الكتلة ثلاثة أخماس من الميل عمقا
and if you compare the expanse of the calving face
وان قارنت هذه الكتلة من الوجه الجليدي المنطقة كلها
to the Tower Bridge in London, about 20 bridges wide.
مع جسر لندن العملاق , حوالي 20 من جسراً عرضا .
Or if you take an American reference, to the U.S. Capitol Building
اوإن اخدت مقياساً أمريكيا , للولايات المتحدة . مبنى البرلمان
and you pack 3,000 Capitol Buildings into that block,
وحزمتم نحو3000 مبني معاً للبرلمان إلي تلك الكتلة ,
it would be equivalent to how large that block was.
ستكون حتما متساوية الى كم كانت تلك الكتلة كبيرة .
75 minutes.
كل ذلك في 75 دقيقة فقط .
Now I've come to the conclusion
الآن قد وصلت الى استنتاج
after spending a lot of time in this climate change world
بعد قضاء الكثير من الوقت في معرفة حول تغير المناخ
that we don't have a problem of economics, technology and public policy.
ليس لدينا مشكلة مع الاقتصاد , التكنولوجيا , والسياسة العامة .
We have a problem of perception.
لدينا مشكلة مع الملاحظة .
The policy and the economics and the technology are serious enough issues,
السياسة وعلم الاقتصاد والتكنولوجيا مواضيع مهمة تماما ,
but we actually can deal with them.
لكن نقدر حاليا أن نتعامل معها .
I'm certain that we can.
أنا متأكد بأننا نقدر .
But what we have is a perception problem
لكن ما لدينا هو مشكلة الملاحظة
because not enough people really get it yet.
لأن الناس التي فهمت هذا ليست كافية لهدا حتى الآن .
You're an elite audience. You get it.
أنتم النخبة المستمعة . توصلتم الى هذا .
Fortunately, a lot of the political leaders in the major countries of the world
لحسن الحظ , الكثير من الرؤساء السياسيون في دول رئيسية من العالم
are an elite audience that for the most part gets it now.
هم تلك النخبة التي تستطيع فعليا أن تدرك هذا الخطر الآن .
But we still need to bring a lot of people along with us.
لكننا لازلنا نحتاج لنجلب الكثير من الناس معنا في هذا .
And that's where I think organizations like TED,
وذلك حيث اعتقد أن منظمات متل تيد ,
like the Extreme Ice Survey can have a terrific impact
مثل التقرير الجليدي المفرط التي تستطيع ان تتناول التأثير الرهيب
on human perception and bring us along.
على المفاهيم الإنساتية ويجذبنا معاً في هذا .
Because I believe we have an opportunity right now.
بسبب اعتقادي انه لدينا فرصة قائمة الآن .
We are nearly on the edge of a crisis,
نحن قريبين من حافة الأزمة ,
but we still have an opportunity to face the greatest challenge
لكن لازال لدينا الفرصة لنواجه أخطر تحدي
of our generation and, in fact, of our century.
لجيلنا و , حقيقة , لهذا القرن .
This is a terrific, terrific call to arms
يكون هدا دعوة للتكاتف
to do the right thing for ourselves and for the future.
لنفعل الشيء الصحيح لأنفسنا وللمستقبل .
I hope that we have the wisdom to let the angels of our better nature
اتمنى أن نكون لدينا الحكمة لنترك الملائكة لطبيعتنا الجيدة
rise to the occasion and do what needs to be done. Thank you.
تنهض للمنافسة وننجز ما لابد من إنجازه . شكرا لكم .
(Applause)
(تصفيق)